<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Evan Heisman's Web Log - eheisman</title><link href="./" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/eheisman.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>./</id><updated>2021-12-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Meteor Scatter Station</title><link href="meteor-scatter-station.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-12-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-12-09:meteor-scatter-station.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Plans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of those magical things that has kept me interested in ham radio all these years has been the idea of bouncing signals off of things, particularly those in space.  I've long wanted to give meteor scatter a try, so I want to get my station set up for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Plans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of those magical things that has kept me interested in ham radio all these years has been the idea of bouncing signals off of things, particularly those in space.  I've long wanted to give meteor scatter a try, so I want to get my station set up for that this winter.  It seems much more within reach than satellite operations (next on my list) or &lt;a class="external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earth%E2%80%93Moon%E2%80%93Earth_communication"&gt;EME communication&lt;/a&gt;.  Satellite repeaters requiring specialized antennas or at least good timing and knowing where to point a handheld antenna, while EME requiring some amplifiers outside of my budget for this hobby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It appears I can use a 2-element beam for 50MHz that my neighbor gave me, along with my IC-706MKIIG radio, and the WSJT-X software.  I want to mount the 50MHz antenna on a mast over my garage, and then get the software and radio set up to try some meteor scatter contacts in the morning before my kid gets up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A few resources I've been refering to.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pages I've looked at to help me assemble this station:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://physics.princeton.edu/pulsar/k1jt/wsjtx.html"&gt;WSJT-X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.pingjockey.net/cgi-bin/pingtalk"&gt;ping jockeys&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.parkerradio.org/community/general/simple-guide-to-meteor-scatter-msk-144/"&gt;Parker Radio Assoc. post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.arrl.org/files/file/QST%2520Binaries/nt0z.pdf"&gt;QST article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://svarc.us/success-with-the-2020-leonids-meteor-shower-on-6-meters/"&gt;K3VAT post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="radio"></category></entry><entry><title>Garden Boxes</title><link href="garden-boxes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-12-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-12-08:garden-boxes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="garden boxes in front yard" src=".\photos\garden_boxesa.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago we decided to move our vegetable garden to the front yard, with the goal of reducing the amount of lawn we had and making use of one of the sunnier and less utilized spots in our yard.  Our existing raised beds had been build by …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="garden boxes in front yard" src=".\photos\garden_boxesa.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago we decided to move our vegetable garden to the front yard, with the goal of reducing the amount of lawn we had and making use of one of the sunnier and less utilized spots in our yard.  Our existing raised beds had been build by a previous owner, placed in the shaddow of a tall hedge running around the back yard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are about 11 inches deep, and roughly 4 feet across for easy access.  We had planned to use these for the &lt;a class="internal" href="squarefootgardening.org/"&gt;"Square Foot Gardening" method&lt;/a&gt;, but since decided that our root vegetables all end up too small due to being crowded.  The boxes are filled with a planting mix from one of our &lt;a class="external" href="http://wenzelnursery.com/"&gt;local garden centers&lt;/a&gt; composed of equal parts soil, mulch, and composted cow manure, which has worked great for growing vegetables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the years since building the first two, I've added two more, and are planning to build two more this winter.  With the four we have we were getting quite a few fresh vegetables and freezing some for the winter.  Six will probably be enough for our family for a while.  They won't entirely replace purchases from the farmers market and grocery store -- there are some veggies that are too tedious to grow.  We mostly stick to tomatoes, peppers, squash, and a few root vegetables.  Leafy greens are difficult to keep pest free, especially from leaf miners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Sliding dovetail joint&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(TODO: add detail of joint)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built these from my own plans out of cedar, using a sliding dovetail joint to attach the sides.  The first time I borrowed a router from a friend and tediously used the only dovetail bit he had to make four passes through the slot to enlarge it to an adequately sized slot for the boards to slide into.  I had built a little fence jig to attach to my friend's router to help with this.  The next year I bought a large dovetail bit and my own router, doing all eight corner pieces at once.  The slot was not quite straight doing this even with a commercial mortising jig, and usually ends up a little loose.  I often tack the boards in place with a brad nailer just to hold them together until I can put soil inside, at which point the pressure on the walls pushes everything into place.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I am going to try individual pieces again, but using a router table.  In previous years as well as this year, I need to make several passes with a narrow straight cutting bit to cut the 3/4" deep hole before making a final pass to carve out the dovetail walls.  I'll let you all know how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Homemade house numbers - or, is a CNC machine worth it?</title><link href="homemade-house-numbers-or-is-a-cnc-machine-worth-it.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-12-04T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-12-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-12-04:homemade-house-numbers-or-is-a-cnc-machine-worth-it.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Around the time I started to get into woodworking, I bought a &lt;a class="external" href="https://wiki.shapeoko.com/index.php/ShapeOko_2"&gt;Shapeoko2 CNC machine&lt;/a&gt; during their crowdfunding campaign.  I had mostly planned to use it for electronics projects, milling single layer circuit boards and making simple enclosures.  My in-laws then asked for larger than normal house numbers as a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Around the time I started to get into woodworking, I bought a &lt;a class="external" href="https://wiki.shapeoko.com/index.php/ShapeOko_2"&gt;Shapeoko2 CNC machine&lt;/a&gt; during their crowdfunding campaign.  I had mostly planned to use it for electronics projects, milling single layer circuit boards and making simple enclosures.  My in-laws then asked for larger than normal house numbers as a holiday gift.  They lived in a retirement community the time and claimed the house numbers were too hard to read from a distance.  I took this as a good opportunity to learn how to use the machine and required software, I could mill them out of MDF and then give them a good coat of an acrylic spraypaint to seal them against the weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="house numbers for inlaws" src=".\photos\house_numbers_2760a.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might have been one of a few CNC projects I completed, I can't actually think of the others.  For a number of reason, I sold the machine and bought a bunch of more traditional woodworking equipment instead.  Since lots of people have compared CNC versus traditional woodworking techniques, I won't try to recap all the differences here.  A quick search on YouTube will yield lots of videos.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the thing that made me sell the machine was the software.  At the time I was using Linux on all my home computers, and the CNC ecosystem for Linux wasn't great.  &lt;a class="external" href="https://librecad.org/"&gt;LibreCAD&lt;/a&gt; is a decent CAD package for two dimensional work, and did a good job for design work.  The Shapeoko's GRBL controller, paired with Universal G-code Sender software worked well for controlling the machine.  The challenge I had was finding a good Computer Aided Manufacturing (CAM) software to convert the 2D CAD drawings to the G-code that tells the what to do. With good reason, this is a challenging bit of software to develop - there are a lot of (literal) moving parts.  Unfortunately, sticking to the Linux environment, the available options were all pretty sub-par.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I've kind of decided to keep computer's out of my shop.  I'd like to learn techniques (both with power and hand tools) that let me use my brain and my hands to build something.  I spend a lot of my work day in front of a computer screen, and I didn't want to add &lt;em&gt;yet another&lt;/em&gt; hobby that kept me sitting in front of a glowing rectangle.  And the original goal of milling circuit boards - someday I want to learn some of the old-school homebrew techniques for building circuits (like Manhattan or dead-bug style construction).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I bought a scroll saw - it's one of several tools that, depending on the size and material) replaced my need for a CNC machine.  It wasn't a great purchase, but I did a few projects with it.  It's a lot faster to print out my design, tack it onto a board, and cut out than it would take me to go through using a buggy piece of CAM software and upload it to the machine.  I ended up doing another set of house numbers using the scroll saw, and I think they came out just as nice as the CNC product would be.  Of course, I ending up &lt;a class="internal" href="toy-cars.html"&gt;getting rid of the scroll saw&lt;/a&gt;, but if I had to do this project again, I would pick up another cheap one over trying to find someone with a CNC machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="house numbers for my house" src=".\photos\house_numbers_1312a.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Shop Improvements</title><link href="shop-improvements.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-27:shop-improvements.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My woodshop is the back half of my garage, which was added as an addition by some previous owner.  There is an obvious gap between the front and back halfs, where a hole was framed up and cut open  I've long wanted to make my shop more usable in the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My woodshop is the back half of my garage, which was added as an addition by some previous owner.  There is an obvious gap between the front and back halfs, where a hole was framed up and cut open  I've long wanted to make my shop more usable in the winter by dividing it off from the garage.  Every winter I use a few electric heaters to warm it up each day that I want to use it.  While I would like to insulate the walls someday, I'm starting with cutting the space to heat in half as a quick way to make the space heaters more effective.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This weekend I framed out a wall, hung a couple of interior doors that were in the garage rafters when I moved in, and used a sheet of fiberboard cover one side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next steps are to close off the right hand side with a plexiglass window to allow a little light and visibilty between halves of the garage.  Then I want to put up some trim to make the doors look a bit more professional and seal off the edges.  And they all need a good cleaning from the dust that has accumulated on them over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="shop wall in progress" src=".\photos\shop_walla.jpg"&gt;
Image of shop wall in progress&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="One view of my shop" src=".\photos\2019-10-17 18.35.29a.jpg"&gt;
A view of my shop in 2019 showing the hole in the from the other side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous shop improvements I made include upgrading the electrical (I contracted this out), added some air filtration equipment, and a couple of additional places to store tools and supplies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>End grain cutting boards</title><link href="end-grain-cutting-boards.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-26:end-grain-cutting-boards.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="end grain cutting boards" src=".\photos\cutting_boardsa.jpg"&gt;
Two of the four cutting boards I made shown next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started making a big end grain cutting board a way of saying thanks to a good friend who catered our baby shower and learned a lot of things along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first thought was …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="end grain cutting boards" src=".\photos\cutting_boardsa.jpg"&gt;
Two of the four cutting boards I made shown next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started making a big end grain cutting board a way of saying thanks to a good friend who catered our baby shower and learned a lot of things along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first thought was to make these big and heavy, with a high contrast checkerboard pattern using one-inch squares as a reference for cutting vegetables.  I was going to make a pair and keep the worse one for myself.  This way I would have two chances at everything, and end up with a nice big cutting board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought the required amount of hard maple and black walnut for this approach only to find out that the black walnut was a lot more difficult to work with.  In particular, cutting the strips of black walnut on my table saw was resulting in the wood binding around the blade, both causing the resulting strip to come out with a bow in it, and stopping the blade, causing the circuit breaker to trip and the lights to go out.  I tried a few upgrades, including putting the ribbing knife back in place (always a good idea!) and buying a rip blade, as I had only been using a combination blade so far.  I also used it as sign that I should upgrade the electrical wiring in my shop, as previously the whole garage was on a single 20A circuit.  I also switched to using a red cherry wood instead of the black walnut.  The contrast between the cherry and maple wasn't quite as impressive, but it looks better than the original would have come out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hand planed most of the 1x1 strips after cutting them down to just a bit oversized.  This was tedious work that I could have easily done with a good setup on the tablesaw, but also really good practice at using a handplane.  Some of the lack of perfect intersections in the grid are due to my planing being a little off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="cutting board strips ready to glue up" src=".\photos\cutting_board_stripsa.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="cutting board strips glued up and clamped" src=".\photos\cutting_board_slab_glue_upa.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After gluing up the strips into a slab, I cross-cut them with my table saw to two inch width sections.  These sections would then be turned end grain up and glued on facegrain in alternating pairs to create the checkerboard effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took these cross-cut sections over to another woodworking friend's shop to use his planer to get them right to just to 1" wide in this dimension.  Using the planeer was not a great idea.  Running the sections through the planer, which could only be done across the grain at this poin, ended up creating all kinds of problems.  As a result, I lost about a third of the cross-cut sections!  The first problem was going across the grain caused a lot of tear-out and breaking segments as it passed under the cutters.  The fibers that were planed off were not short, but 2" long bits of wood, which quickly clogged the planer and chip collector it was hooked up to.  At some point during the session I found out my friend had not really used the planer much since buying it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I got these back to my shop, I glued the face grain sides together, alternating the two types of sections to create the checkerboard pattern.  This took a lot of clamps, cauls, and patience.  Finally I sanded them successively to 220 grit, put a slight roundover on every side, and oiled them with butchers block oil.  My spouse thought I was a little obsessed with how nice they looked after all that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making a second set&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I was finishing the big checkerboard set, I ended up doing another pair using the scraps of walnut, with a little bit of the cherry and maple for contrast.  I only used my hand planes to shape these, but as I wasn't going for perfect 1" square strips, I was able to get a little more creative in the pattern.  I glued up three different slabs, crosscut them, and then mixed and matched, flipping and shifting the pieces to get a more random looking pattern to them.  After making both sets of cutting boards, I really like these a whole lot better.  I kept a slightly smaller one and gave the larger of these to a friend who was moving away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The big one is just a little too heavy (1.5" thick, surface area is 11" by 10").  It is a great size for heavy-duty project cooking where lots of vegetable prep is needed, but a little too heavy to want to get out day-to-day cooking.  I am glad I didn't make it any bigger by surface area, like I would have if I hadn't lost so many pieces to the power planer.  If I made one again, I would target closer to 1" thick.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The small one is just a little too small (8.5" by 5") to use for much, but regularly gets used for cutting up fruit or cheese, or when we just need to dice one or two cups of a veggie.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My bigger one is a bit warped due to me being hasty while gluing it up, so I use a towel or piece of drawer liner under it to help keep it from rocking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After their first wash the grain got raised a little bit by the water causing them to loose a bit of their smoothness.  I sanded these a second time which took care of the rough texture.  If I ever make another one as a gift, I want to remember to do this!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both get used almost every day!  It was a great project to learn a lot about woodworking, and I'd recommend anyone wanting to do a useful project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Hand planes</title><link href="hand-planes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-26:hand-planes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before I started woodworking, I always thought handplanes were a quirky part of the woodworking hobby, something that people collected but not commonly used.  I bought one #4 plane from Harbor Freight during my cutting board project to help square up the strips.  I figured it was a lot cheaper …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before I started woodworking, I always thought handplanes were a quirky part of the woodworking hobby, something that people collected but not commonly used.  I bought one #4 plane from Harbor Freight during my cutting board project to help square up the strips.  I figured it was a lot cheaper than buying a planer or other pieces of power equipment.  In trying to make it actually work, I found out these are still serious tools, and lots of craftsman do really amazing woodworking by hand.  While there are a number of YouTube channels dedicated to hand tool woodworking, the one I most recommend is &lt;a class="external" href="https://www.youtube.com/c/RexKrueger/"&gt;Rex Kruger (YouTube)&lt;/a&gt;.  He has a bunch of great videos about restoring and using old and cheap tools, and does a great job explaining the how and why of these tools and techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="wood planes lined up on workbench" src=".\photos\planesa.jpg"&gt;
wood planes lined up on workbench&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An inventory of my hand planes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From left to right in the photo above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Harbor Freight block plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty much useless, occasionally use to knock off some sharp edges.  Came with the #4 plane as a box set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dunlop block plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likely belonged to my grandfather, I found this still in the box in my dad's garage.  I use this one regularly for trimming up the ends of boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Craftsman block plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very similar model, bought at an antique store near my parent's house before I knew about the one my dad had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Harbor Freight No. 4 "Scrub" Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first plane I bought and found impossible to use out of the box.  (a plane, from harbor freight, that wasn't ready to go?  you don't say...)  I later gave the blade a heavy camber to use it as a scrub plane which it does really well at due to the wide throat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dunlop No. 4 Smoothing Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likely belonged to my grandfather, kept in the original box for years.  I love using this plane, it works really well for finishing a project.  My dad pointed me to these after buying the Stanley #5 and Craftsman Block Plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stanley No. 5 Jack Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bought at an antique store near my parents house.  This is really my "jack" of all trades plane, using it for everything from stock prep to planing edges for joints.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning Tower</title><link href="learning-tower.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-26:learning-tower.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="learning tower in kitchen" src=".\photos\learning_tower_finisheda.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Concept&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I modified &lt;a class="external" href="https://www.ana-white.com/woodworking-projects/littlest-helper-tower"&gt;these plans from Ana White&lt;/a&gt; by removing the arch shape and using mortise and tenon joints instead of the pocket screws.  I could have easily done it with the pocket screws and had a great result, but I  wanted to challenge myself doing a whole bunch of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="learning tower in kitchen" src=".\photos\learning_tower_finisheda.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Concept&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I modified &lt;a class="external" href="https://www.ana-white.com/woodworking-projects/littlest-helper-tower"&gt;these plans from Ana White&lt;/a&gt; by removing the arch shape and using mortise and tenon joints instead of the pocket screws.  I could have easily done it with the pocket screws and had a great result, but I  wanted to challenge myself doing a whole bunch of morises and tenons joints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used this project to practice making mortise and tenon joints, as my first real project (besides my &lt;a class="internal" href="workbench-and-stand.html"&gt;miter saw stand&lt;/a&gt;) used a tenon jig that I made to fit over the fence of my table saw.  The mortises were made using my drill press.  I assembled two of the sides before adding the mortises for the biggest side panels, and drilling out the mortises on these pieces with the drill press was the most awkward step.  The tenon jig was not perfect - I had to constantly apply a sideways pressure into the fence to keep it from wobbling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="tenon jig made from MDF and toggle clamp" src=".\photos\tenon_jiga.jpg"&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great project, and with the mortise and tenon joints it gave me a chance to challenge myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The adjustable floor has worked well as my kid has grown.  We probably won't use it all the way to the bottom rung, as a step stool might work just as well at that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="learning tower in progress, unpainted" src=".\photos\learning_tower_constructiona.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My only complaint about the project is that I used some housepaint to finish it.  I would have left it with just wood finish, but there were a number of blemishes in the wood when I bought it and more that I added while planing the pieces.  I patched these with some wood filler.  I put the paint on in a way that left a lot of drips and blops.  Since it is used by a preschooler for all kinds of snacks and other activities, it been picking up all kinds of smudges and dirt, and I haven't found a good cleaner that actually removes them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Toy cars</title><link href="toy-cars.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-26:toy-cars.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have wanted to make more wooden toys for my kid, and after purchasing a used scroll saw, I was able to make a couple of toy cars like this out of some scrap elm I had in the shop.  I had bought the wheels from a wood supply shop …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have wanted to make more wooden toys for my kid, and after purchasing a used scroll saw, I was able to make a couple of toy cars like this out of some scrap elm I had in the shop.  I had bought the wheels from a wood supply shop in Portland on a visit, although I think any chain craft store might have them.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up making two, the one pictured below, and a newer one with a few small issues addressed.  The length of the axles and the roundness of the axle holes is critical to get them to roll well, the second car I made works much better.  The photo of the car being finished shows how I messed up drilling the hole for the front axle, it is not quite round.  The second car also had some paste wax applied to the inside of the axle holes before assembly.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One remaining issue is the size of these cars - they ended up being just a little too big for my kid to play with when I made them (around 18 months old).  I would reduce the size by about a third in all dimensions if I ever make more of these.  The wheels already look a little too big, but I think having them be a more managable size would make them more fun to play with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I got rid of the scroll saw --  I had bought it used, without any blades.  As the owner demonstrated it and told me his mother-in-law had used it for some crafts, I thought it was good to go.  After getting it home and set up, I noticed a few parts showed some damage to the blade holder that made it rattle when in use, and difficult to tension.  As a result I broke quite a few blades trying to complete these toy cars and another project.  I might have been able to craft a few replacement parts, but decided it was a better use of my time to practice with a coping or turning saw for these kinds of projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="toy car complete" src=".\photos\2019-08-19 06.29.32_toy_cara.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="toy car having a polyurathane finish applied" src=".\photos\2019-08-17 13.58.15a.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO: trace cars to create template with 66% of current size, upload template here&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Desk</title><link href="desk.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-25:desk.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Concept&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2020, I realized I was going to need a better desk to continue working from home with, so I decided it was time to finally build one.  This had been a goal of mine when getting into woodworking, but given the circumstances, I thought it was a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Concept&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2020, I realized I was going to need a better desk to continue working from home with, so I decided it was time to finally build one.  This had been a goal of mine when getting into woodworking, but given the circumstances, I thought it was a good time to take a first shot at one.  I ended up building something like a basic table, a little larger than most commercial desks, and gave it legs and supports at the far sides.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The desk-top is assembled from pieces of locally source cherry that I joined with a borrowed biscuit joiner and then planed flat.  I put a slight half-inch bevel around the outside with a handplane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top came out great - I really took the time to learn to handplane it smooth and finish with shellac.  It has a few blemishes from places where the grain switches direction and my handplaning messed it up, but not bad for my first try at a 'tabletop'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few things I'd like to improve about this desk in the future: 
- The legs ended up being extremely light weight and quickly thrown together, and while they serve their purpose, someday I want to replace them with something more study.  It's also about two inches too high.  The biggest reason the legs ended up the way they did was that I didn't buy enough wood to begin with.
- It doesn't have any storage.  As shown in the photo, I have some milk crates holding various things and a printer under it.  Someday I might build a portable cabinet that fits under it and holds these kind of things.
- I'd like to add a tray or shelf near the back to help with cable organization and to hold up my laptop and monitor at the same level.  Maybe for cable organization to add a tray under the desk surface and use desk grommets to provide access for cables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plans I had sketched out show some of these additional features and how I'd really like to do the legs - I'm including them below (without commentary) as a friend had asked about my design process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Desk with office equipement and other stuff on it, pardon the mess!" src=".\photos\2020-12-08_deska.jpg"&gt;
Desk with office equipment and other stuff on it, pardon the mess!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Plans&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="overall sizing and leg detail" src=".\photos\deskplans_1a.jpg"&gt;
Overall design and leg detail, along with a side sketch of a knitting box I still need to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="material list" src=".\photos\deskplans_2a.jpg"&gt;
A brief cut list and bill of materials to inform my shopping.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Owl House</title><link href="owl-house.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-25:owl-house.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few years ago we decided to put a screech owl box in our big oak tree.  We regularly hear them calling at night during the summer when our windows are open.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a class="external" href="https://wdfw.wa.gov/species-habitats/living/woodworking-projects"&gt;plans from WDFW&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="external" href="https://nestwatch.org/learn/all-about-birdhouses/birds/eastern-screech-owl/"&gt;Cornell Lab of Ornithology&lt;/a&gt;, which I ended up using the WDFW plans …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few years ago we decided to put a screech owl box in our big oak tree.  We regularly hear them calling at night during the summer when our windows are open.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a class="external" href="https://wdfw.wa.gov/species-habitats/living/woodworking-projects"&gt;plans from WDFW&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="external" href="https://nestwatch.org/learn/all-about-birdhouses/birds/eastern-screech-owl/"&gt;Cornell Lab of Ornithology&lt;/a&gt;, which I ended up using the WDFW plans.  I made the box from a piece of western red cedar from the lumberyard, and with the help of my dad got it tied up to the tree.  It has been up for a few years, although we only had an owl visit once to get shelter from a snowstorm.  So far, it's mostly be home to the yard's resident squirels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="owl house assembled" src=".\photos\2018-10-20_owl_housea.jpg"&gt;
owl house as assembled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="owl house in use" src=".\photos\owl_house_in_usea.jpg"&gt;
owl house in tree with a screech owl poking it's head out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Workbench and Stand</title><link href="workbench-and-stand.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-19:workbench-and-stand.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here's a few bits of shop furniture I've built and my thoughts about what I would do different next time.  I figure shop furniture is a great place to learn new techniques without worrying about aesthetics.  I often use construction lumber and recycled materials for these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Miter saw stand&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concept …&lt;/h2&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here's a few bits of shop furniture I've built and my thoughts about what I would do different next time.  I figure shop furniture is a great place to learn new techniques without worrying about aesthetics.  I often use construction lumber and recycled materials for these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Miter saw stand&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my first attempt at mortise and tenon joints.  A friend gave me the cabinet drawers out of a kitchen he was remodeling, which worked perfectly for adding some storage to this project.  I used my drill press to hog out the mortises and a set of chisels to clean them up.  I built a basic tenon jig for my table saw.  Both were pretty rough and I was worried the whole assembly wouldn't go together well after a test fit.  I had planned for side panels made from peg board for storing additional tools and sawblades, and once I added these, the whole thing was a lot more stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use the bigger drawers near the bottom for storing various smaller tools and jigs, and the top drawer for all my screws, nails, and other fasteners.  I made a simple set of dividers from some MDF and stuck them down in there.  This mostly works well, but it is an odd place to put all of those.
&lt;img alt="miter saw stand shown from the front" src=".\photos\2019-11-26 20.02.53_miter_saw_standa.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The castors on the bottom are also a bit funky, I had put two with swivels and two without, to save some money, but this arrangement doesn't provide much maneuverability when moving around the shop.  As a result, I often end up lifting one side off the ground to roll it around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Workbench&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built this workbench without knowing what I was doing and has grown organically with my needs.  The base was &lt;a class="external" href="https://woodgears.ca/workbench/"&gt;inspired by Matthias Wandel's plans&lt;/a&gt; while the top was roughly in the english-style bench... but I would call it a picnic table top.  I've since added a vise, tool well, more bracing, and some extra shelves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's due to be replaced someday as it is a little shakey and the top is slightly warped due to a slight twist to the frame.  I've tried planing the top a few times, and it is free of any big bumps, but the warp/twist is a bit of problem when working on large panels.  It'll probably get repurposed as another bench for gardening or light metal work when I do replace it.  I've since added more bracing to the back to keep it from racking when I am really vigorously planing a piece of wood, and another storage shelf for tools.  There is also a tool well off to one side of the bench that I use for storing various bits of workholding gear like bench dogs and holdfasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="workbench as originally built" src=".\photos\2018-04-28 15.00.30a.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Vise&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Harbor Freight carpenters vise that I started with is great for small pieces, but sticks up over the edge of the bench.
To help fix this, I built a very simple vise from a piece of hard maple, and two 8" long 3/4" diameter bolts which a friend welded handles onto.  The rough idea was from &lt;a class="external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Mr7RKz8V4Y8"&gt;One Minute Woodworking's video on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;, although looking back at it, my plans have the bolts mounted backwards from theirs.  It was dirt cheap, the maple might have been the most expensive piece.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gets plenty of grip for handplaning and helping hold pieces to the bench, but turning both handles to tighten and loosen it can be a little tedious.  The handles on the bolts get in the way sometime, next time I would do some kind of wooden knobs and epoxy them on.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="workbench vise" src=".\photos\2019-04-16 20.46.41_visea.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Projects</title><link href="projects.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-13:projects.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Woodworking&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ongoing:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="shop-improvements.html"&gt;Shop improvements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning to use &lt;a class="internal" href="hand-planes.html"&gt;hand planes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Completed:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="workbench-and-stand.html"&gt;Workbench and Miter Saw Stand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="desk.html"&gt;Desk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="owl-house.html"&gt;Screen Owl Box&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="toy-cars.html"&gt;Toy cars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="end-grain-cutting-boards.html"&gt;Cutting boards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="learning-tower.html"&gt;Learning Tower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="garden-boxes.html"&gt;Garden Boxes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Someday:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solid wood base for custom record player&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New legs for my desk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Ham Radio&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ongoing:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remote Antenna Switch and Antenna Rotator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://lcwo.net/profile/kc2ihx"&gt;Learn …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Woodworking&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ongoing:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="shop-improvements.html"&gt;Shop improvements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning to use &lt;a class="internal" href="hand-planes.html"&gt;hand planes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Completed:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="workbench-and-stand.html"&gt;Workbench and Miter Saw Stand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="desk.html"&gt;Desk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="owl-house.html"&gt;Screen Owl Box&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="toy-cars.html"&gt;Toy cars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="end-grain-cutting-boards.html"&gt;Cutting boards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="learning-tower.html"&gt;Learning Tower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="garden-boxes.html"&gt;Garden Boxes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Someday:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solid wood base for custom record player&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New legs for my desk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Ham Radio&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ongoing:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remote Antenna Switch and Antenna Rotator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://lcwo.net/profile/kc2ihx"&gt;Learn CW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://github.com/indiahotelxray/dds60-siggen"&gt;DDS-60 VFO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Someday:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;APRS I-Gate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="meteor-scatter.html"&gt;Meteor scatter station&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VHF/UHF Rover&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Computers/Programming&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ongoing:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="internal" href="eheisman.github.io"&gt;this blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Completed:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Python&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://github.com/indiahotelxray/brickgame"&gt;brick breaker game&lt;/a&gt; - written in Python with &lt;code&gt;pyxel&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;R&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://github.com/indiahotelxray/PickUpGameMonteCarlo"&gt;Monte Carlo Analysis of Basketball Pick-up Game&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frequency Curve Explorer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://github.com/eheisman/dssrip"&gt;&lt;code&gt;dssrip&lt;/code&gt; - R package&lt;/a&gt; for reading HEC-DSS files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://github.com/eheisman/hydroutils"&gt;&lt;code&gt;hydroutils&lt;/code&gt; - R package&lt;/a&gt; with basic functions for hydrologic statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Someday:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email migration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Woodworking resources</title><link href="woodworking-resources.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-13:woodworking-resources.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Video Channels&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.youtube.com/c/RexKrueger/"&gt;Rex Kruger (YouTube)&lt;/a&gt; - Rex's videos really taught me how to sharpen and use handplanes and I really appreciate his approach to making woodworking with hand tools more accessible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.youtube.com/user/stevinmarin"&gt;Steve Ramsey (YouTube)&lt;/a&gt; - Lots of good introductory videos for power tool woodworking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.newyankee.com/"&gt;New Yankee Workshop (not YouTube)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Books&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.woodworkforhumans.com/"&gt;Rex Kruger's …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Video Channels&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.youtube.com/c/RexKrueger/"&gt;Rex Kruger (YouTube)&lt;/a&gt; - Rex's videos really taught me how to sharpen and use handplanes and I really appreciate his approach to making woodworking with hand tools more accessible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.youtube.com/user/stevinmarin"&gt;Steve Ramsey (YouTube)&lt;/a&gt; - Lots of good introductory videos for power tool woodworking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.newyankee.com/"&gt;New Yankee Workshop (not YouTube)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Books&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.woodworkforhumans.com/"&gt;Rex Kruger's Everyday Woodworking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Shops&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jensen's Hardwood (&lt;a class="external" href="https://www.jensenhardwoods.com/"&gt;web&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a class="external" href="https://www.facebook.com/jensenhardwoods/"&gt;facebook&lt;/a&gt;) - great place to buy hardwood in the Walla Walla Valley.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>What's here</title><link href="whats-here.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-11:whats-here.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;About Me&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a civil engineer (water resources engineer) by training who has been doing more and more software engineering work.  My job consists of maintaining and upgrading computer models of watersheds and reserviors.  When I am not doing that, I dabble in &lt;a class="internal" href="category/wood.html"&gt;woodworking&lt;/a&gt;, birding, organic gardening, photography, and &lt;a class="internal" href="category/radio.html"&gt;ham …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;About Me&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a civil engineer (water resources engineer) by training who has been doing more and more software engineering work.  My job consists of maintaining and upgrading computer models of watersheds and reserviors.  When I am not doing that, I dabble in &lt;a class="internal" href="category/wood.html"&gt;woodworking&lt;/a&gt;, birding, organic gardening, photography, and &lt;a class="internal" href="category/radio.html"&gt;ham radio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What do I want to do here:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keep track of ongoing hobby projects, provide myself some accountability on them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;share information or thoughts relevant to those projects&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kind of a public version of my personal OneNote&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;post less on social media and more on the old-web&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keep track of interesting things I read&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What about the old blog?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, &lt;a class="external" href="https://eaheisman.blogspot.com"&gt;that one with three or four posts about reading HEC-DSS files in R?&lt;/a&gt;.  I'm going to leave that up for now with comments turned off, but most of the content is on &lt;a class="external" href="https://github.com/eheisman"&gt;my github profile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Why the blog name?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phonetic alphabet for the last three letters of my amateur radio callsign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What are my short term goals for programming?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn a more modern IDE that I can use for work (Java, Python, R) and home (Python and R).  This probably means Visual Studio Code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally upgrade to skills to Python 3 (in 2021! I mean... 2022!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>New blog</title><link href="new-blog.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-09:new-blog.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;TODO items (updated occasionally)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get a decent theme working&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turns out your pelican-themes directory needs to actually have themes in it!  I naively cloned the &lt;code&gt;pelican-themes&lt;/code&gt; github repo and got empty directories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make markdown first level headers slightly smaller than post title.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h2&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; css to make slightly smaller than …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;TODO items (updated occasionally)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get a decent theme working&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turns out your pelican-themes directory needs to actually have themes in it!  I naively cloned the &lt;code&gt;pelican-themes&lt;/code&gt; github repo and got empty directories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make markdown first level headers slightly smaller than post title.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h2&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; css to make slightly smaller than &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: updated theme's main.css, maybe there should be a better approach.  Tried adding a second css file to template's base.html.  Learned about the &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; operator in css.  New css file works well enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert header image - on hold&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;need to modify base.html template; identify file, add static image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;upload a few photos of woodworking projects - in progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;upload some short descriptions of programming projects - in progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add caption style using &lt;code&gt;img + p&lt;/code&gt; in css&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="computers"></category></entry></feed>