<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Evan Heisman's Web Log - eheisman</title><link href="./" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/eheisman.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>./</id><updated>2021-11-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Desk</title><link href="desk.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-25:desk.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Concept&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2020, I realized I was going to need a better desk to continue working from home with, so I decided it was time to finally build one.  This had been a goal of mine when getting into woodworking, but given the circumstances, I thought it was a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Concept&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2020, I realized I was going to need a better desk to continue working from home with, so I decided it was time to finally build one.  This had been a goal of mine when getting into woodworking, but given the circumstances, I thought it was a good time to take a first shot at one.  I ended up building something like a basic table, a little larger than most commercial desks, and gave it legs and supports at the far sides.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The desk-top is assembled from pieces of locally source cherry that I joined with a borrowed biscuit joiner and then planed flat.  I put a slight half-inch bevel around the outside with a handplane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top came out great - I really took the time to learn to handplane it smooth and finish with shellac.  It has a few blemishes from places where the grain switches direction and my handplaning messed it up, but not bad for my first try at a 'tabletop'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few things I'd like to improve about this desk in the future: 
- The legs ended up being extremely light weight and quickly thrown together, and while they serve their purpose, someday I want to replace them with something more study.  It's also about two inches too high.  The biggest reason the legs ended up the way they did was that I didn't buy enough wood to begin with.
- It doesn't have any storage.  As shown in the photo, I have some milk crates holding various things and a printer under it.  Someday I might build a portable cabinet that fits under it and holds these kind of things.
- I'd like to add a tray or shelf near the back to help with cable organization and to hold up my laptop and monitor at the same level.  Maybe for cable organization to add a tray under the desk surface and use desk grommets to provide access for cables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plans I had sketched out show some of these additional features and how I'd really like to do the legs - I'm including them below (without commentary) as a friend had asked about my design process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Desk with office equipement and other stuff on it, pardon the mess!" src="./images/2020-12-08_desk.jpg"&gt;
Desk with office equipment and other stuff on it, pardon the mess!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Plans&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="overall sizing and leg detail" src="./images/deskplans_1.jpg"&gt;
Overall design and leg detail, along with a side sketch of a knitting box I still need to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="material list" src="./images/deskplans_2.jpg"&gt;
A brief cut list and bill of materials to inform my shopping.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Workbench and Stand</title><link href="workbench-and-stand.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-19:workbench-and-stand.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here's a few bits of shop furniture I've built and my thoughts about what I would do different next time.  I figure shop furniture is a great place to learn new techniques without worrying about aesthetics.  I often use construction lumber and recycled materials for these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Miter saw stand&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concept …&lt;/h2&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here's a few bits of shop furniture I've built and my thoughts about what I would do different next time.  I figure shop furniture is a great place to learn new techniques without worrying about aesthetics.  I often use construction lumber and recycled materials for these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Miter saw stand&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my first attempt at mortise and tenon joints.  A friend gave me the cabinet drawers out of a kitchen he was remodeling, which worked perfectly for adding some storage to this project.  I used my drill press to hog out the mortises and a set of chisels to clean them up.  I built a basic tenon jig for my table saw.  Both were pretty rough and I was worried the whole assembly wouldn't go together well after a test fit.  I had planned for side panels made from peg board for storing additional tools and sawblades, and once I added these, the whole thing was a lot more stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use the bigger drawers near the bottom for storing various smaller tools and jigs, and the top drawer for all my screws, nails, and other fasteners.  I made a simple set of dividers from some MDF and stuck them down in there.  This mostly works well, but it is an odd place to put all of those.
&lt;img alt="miter saw stand shown from the front" src="./images/2019-11-26 20.02.53_miter_saw_stand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The castors on the bottom are also a bit funky, I had put two with swivels and two without, to save some money, but this arrangement doesn't provide much maneuverability when moving around the shop.  As a result, I often end up lifting one side off the ground to roll it around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Workbench&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built this workbench without knowing what I was doing and has grown organically with my needs.  The base was &lt;a href="https://woodgears.ca/workbench/"&gt;inspired by Matthias Wandel's plans&lt;/a&gt; while the top was roughly in the english-style bench... but I would call it a picnic table top.  I've since added a vise, tool well, more bracing, and some extra shelves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's due to be replaced someday as it is a little shakey and the top is slightly warped due to a slight twist to the frame.  I've tried planing the top a few times, and it is free of any big bumps, but the warp/twist is a bit of problem when working on large panels.  It'll probably get repurposed as another bench for gardening or light metal work when I do replace it.  I've since added more bracing to the back to keep it from racking when I am really vigorously planing a piece of wood, and another storage shelf for tools.  There is also a tool well off to one side of the bench that I use for storing various bits of workholding gear like bench dogs and holdfasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="workbench as originally built" src="./images/2018-04-28 15.00.30.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Vise&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Harbor Freight carpenters vise that I started with is great for small pieces, but sticks up over the edge of the bench.
To help fix this, I built a very simple vise from a piece of hard maple, and two 8" long 3/4" diameter bolts which a friend welded handles onto.  The rough idea was from &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Mr7RKz8V4Y8"&gt;One Minute Woodworking's video on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;, although looking back at it, my plans have the bolts mounted backwards from theirs.  It was dirt cheap, the maple might have been the most expensive piece.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gets plenty of grip for handplaning and helping hold pieces to the bench, but turning both handles to tighten and loosen it can be a little tedious.  The handles on the bolts get in the way sometime, next time I would do some kind of wooden knobs and epoxy them on.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="workbench vise" src="./images/2019-04-16 20.46.41_vise.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Projects</title><link href="projects.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-13:projects.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Woodworking&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ongoing:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./shop_improvements.html"&gt;Shop improvements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./wood_planes.html"&gt;wood planes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Completed:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./cutting_boards.html"&gt;Cutting boards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./workbench_and_stand.html"&gt;Workbench and Miter Saw Stand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./learning_tower.html"&gt;Learning Tower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./desk.html"&gt;Desk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./garden_boxes.html"&gt;Garden Boxes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./owl_box_in_the_middle_of_the_street.html"&gt;Screen Owl Box&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./toy_cars.html"&gt;Toy cars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Someday:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solid wood base for custom record player&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New legs for my desk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Ham Radio&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ongoing:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remote Antenna Switch and Antenna Rotator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://lcwo.net/profile/kc2ihx"&gt;Learn CW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DDS-60 VFO …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Woodworking&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ongoing:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./shop_improvements.html"&gt;Shop improvements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./wood_planes.html"&gt;wood planes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Completed:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./cutting_boards.html"&gt;Cutting boards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./workbench_and_stand.html"&gt;Workbench and Miter Saw Stand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./learning_tower.html"&gt;Learning Tower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./desk.html"&gt;Desk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./garden_boxes.html"&gt;Garden Boxes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./owl_box_in_the_middle_of_the_street.html"&gt;Screen Owl Box&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="./toy_cars.html"&gt;Toy cars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Someday:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solid wood base for custom record player&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New legs for my desk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Ham Radio&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ongoing:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remote Antenna Switch and Antenna Rotator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://lcwo.net/profile/kc2ihx"&gt;Learn CW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DDS-60 VFO&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Someday:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;APRS I-Gate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meteor scatter station&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FT8 station or WSPR beacon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Computers/Programming&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ongoing:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="eheisman.github.io"&gt;this blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Completed:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Python&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/indiahotelxray/pyxelbreaker"&gt;&lt;code&gt;pyxel&lt;/code&gt; brick breaker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;R&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/indiahotelxray/PickUpGameMonteCarlo"&gt;Monte Carlo Analysis of Basketball Pick-up Game&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frequency Curve Explorer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/eheisman/dssrip"&gt;&lt;code&gt;dssrip&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - R package&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/eheisman/hydroutils"&gt;&lt;code&gt;hydroutils&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Some basic functions for hydrologic statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Someday:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email migration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Shop Improvements</title><link href="shop-improvements.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-13:shop-improvements.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I finally decided to get my woodshop cleaned up and more usable in the winter by dividing it out.  Every winter I use a few electric heaters to warm it up each day that I want to use it.  While I would like to insulate it and put up solid …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I finally decided to get my woodshop cleaned up and more usable in the winter by dividing it out.  Every winter I use a few electric heaters to warm it up each day that I want to use it.  While I would like to insulate it and put up solid walls to hang stuff on, I'm starting with cutting the space to heat in half.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/path/to/img.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Woodworking resources</title><link href="woodworking-resources.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-13:woodworking-resources.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Video Channels&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/RexKrueger/"&gt;Rex Kruger (YouTube)&lt;/a&gt; - Rex's videos really taught me how to sharpen and use handplanes and I really appreciate his approach to making woodworking with hand tools more accessible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/stevinmarin"&gt;Steve Ramsey (YouTube)&lt;/a&gt; - Lots of good introductory videos for power tool woodworking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.newyankee.com/"&gt;New Yankee Workshop (not YouTube)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Books&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.woodworkforhumans.com/"&gt;Rex Kruger's …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Video Channels&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/RexKrueger/"&gt;Rex Kruger (YouTube)&lt;/a&gt; - Rex's videos really taught me how to sharpen and use handplanes and I really appreciate his approach to making woodworking with hand tools more accessible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/stevinmarin"&gt;Steve Ramsey (YouTube)&lt;/a&gt; - Lots of good introductory videos for power tool woodworking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.newyankee.com/"&gt;New Yankee Workshop (not YouTube)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Books&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.woodworkforhumans.com/"&gt;Rex Kruger's Everyday Woodworking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Shops&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jensen's Hardwood (&lt;a href="https://www.jensenhardwoods.com/"&gt;web&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/jensenhardwoods/"&gt;facebook&lt;/a&gt;) - great place to buy hardwood in the Walla Walla Valley.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>What's here</title><link href="whats-here.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-11:whats-here.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;About Me&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a civil engineer (water resources engineer) by training who has been doing more and more software engineering work.  My job consists of maintaining and upgrading computer models of watersheds and reserviors.  When I am not doing that, I dabble in &lt;a href="./category/wood.html"&gt;woodworking&lt;/a&gt;, birding, organic gardening, photography, and &lt;a href="./category/radio.html"&gt;ham …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;About Me&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a civil engineer (water resources engineer) by training who has been doing more and more software engineering work.  My job consists of maintaining and upgrading computer models of watersheds and reserviors.  When I am not doing that, I dabble in &lt;a href="./category/wood.html"&gt;woodworking&lt;/a&gt;, birding, organic gardening, photography, and &lt;a href="./category/radio.html"&gt;ham radio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What do I want to do here:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keep track of ongoing hobby projects, provide myself some public accountability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;share information or thoughts relevant to those projects&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kind of a public version of my personal OneNote&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;post less on social media and more on the old-web&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keep track of interesting things I read&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What about the old blog?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, &lt;a href="https://eaheisman.blogspot.com"&gt;that one with three or four posts about reading HEC-DSS files in R?&lt;/a&gt;.  I'm going to leave that up for now with comments turned off, but most of the content is on &lt;a href="https://github.com/eheisman"&gt;my github profile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What are my short term goals for programming?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn a more modern IDE that I can use for work (Java, Python, R) and home (Python and R).  This probably means Visual Studio Code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally upgrade to skills to Python 3 (in 2021! I mean... 2022!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>New blog</title><link href="new-blog.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>eheisman</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-11-09:new-blog.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;TODO items (updated 2021-11-13):&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get a decent theme working&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turns out your pelican-themes directory needs to actually have themes in it!  I naively cloned the &lt;code&gt;pelican-themes&lt;/code&gt; github repo and got empty directories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make markdown first level headers slightly smaller than post title.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h2&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; css to make slightly smaller than …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;TODO items (updated 2021-11-13):&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get a decent theme working&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turns out your pelican-themes directory needs to actually have themes in it!  I naively cloned the &lt;code&gt;pelican-themes&lt;/code&gt; github repo and got empty directories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make markdown first level headers slightly smaller than post title.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h2&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; css to make slightly smaller than &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: updated theme's main.css, maybe there should be a better approach.  Tried adding a second css file to template's base.html.  Learned about the &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; operator in css.  New css file works well enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert header image - on hold&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;need to modify base.html template; identify file, add static image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;upload a few photos of woodworking projects - in progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;upload some short descriptions of programming projects - in progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="computers"></category></entry></feed>